[Music]
foreign
this is John kiriaku a retired American
spy his 14-year career as a CIA officer
was impressive by any measure the agency
deployed kiriaku all over the world in
Pakistan a year after the 9 11 attacks
he led in operation to capture a
high-level Al-Qaeda official known as
Abu zubaida the cia's treatment of
suveda and other detainees would
eventually lead to kiriaku's falling out
with the agency
beta was the first person to be
subjected to the cia's so-called
enhanced interrogation techniques the
U.S government would later acknowledge
the practice was torture
in the immediate aftermath of 9 11.
we did some things that were wrong
we did a whole lot of things that were
right
but we tortured some folks the torture
is depicted in a series of sketches by
abusiveda detainees were subjected to
physical attacks they were put in
various painful stress positions for
long periods of time
waterboarding was a common practice that
involves choking a victim by filling
their throat with a steady stream of
water making them feel as if they're
drowning in slow motion
journalists had long sought official
admission that these practices were
taking place
it wasn't until John kiriaku's 2007
interview with an ABC news reporter that
Washington's Open Secret about
government sanctioned torture was
finally confirmed if the American public
was to see somebody even abusabeta being
waterboarded what would you guess I
think it would be objectionable
it's it's
sort of a violent thing to to see or to
go through
kiriaku who had retired nearly four
years earlier had become the first CIA
official to confirm that the agency used
torture the personal consequences form
since have been enormous after the
interview kiriaku lost his lucrative
corporate job it became the subject of a
lengthy FBI investigation
in 2012 he was charged with multiple
counts of revealing classified
information to journalists
he faced the possibility of 35 years in
jail
part of a deal with prosecutors kiriaku
pled guilty to a single count and was
sentenced to 30 months in federal prison
eight years after being released he
maintains the case against him was
political and that his decision to speak
out will forever be on the right side of
History basil rahan the interview
only one person ended up doing any
prison time over the cia's torture
program
and here's the rub it was not a torturer
it was the man from the CIA
who ended up exposing the program and
confirming that the orders came from the
very top I am delighted to tell you that
he's joined us today on the interview
John kiriaku joins us now really good to
have you on the program John it's been
quite a ride for you over the past
couple of decades are you comfortable
with the with the term whistleblower
when people Google you when they think
about you you're the CIA whistleblower
guy
it actually took me a long time to get
to that point uh I in the beginning I
never called myself a whistleblower I
didn't think that I was a whistleblower
I was just a normal person who saw an
illegality and went public with it it
was my attorneys who had to finally
convince me that I was a whistleblower
when you did that interview in 2007
while you were while you were sitting
there and revealing what you had
revealed saying that yes waterboarding
was policy yes it came from the top yes
this is what we did in the so-called War
on Terror at that moment in time did you
think my life is going to change now I'm
going to end up in jail
or was it somewhat nonchalant did you it
was it only the overreaction of of the
CIA and the FBI and everybody else which
then
made it Dawn on you that this could be
big and you could be in big trouble
I really do
you get done anything wrong in fact my
wife went with me that day to ABC News
and sat just off camera and when I
finished the interview I said how did I
do she said great I said I didn't say
anything classified did I she said no
you did great I had no idea that it was
going to be a major International story
uh that it became in the next day or so
and in fact the say reported me to the
FBI the very next day for having
committed the crime of revealing
classified information the FBI
investigated me for a full year from
December of 2007 until December of 2008
and then elected to not charge me with a
crime they said that that the
information was the worst kept secret in
Washington and that I would not be
charged with a crime what they
eventually
came after you with or what had
eventually stuck when you when you had
the plea deal was that you had disclosed
an undercover CIA operative's name to a
journalist so it wasn't about
whistleblowing in terms of torture and
all of that even though we know that
that's the reason why they were alerted
to you being a possible threat
when you when you made that deal tell me
a little bit about the thought process
and and how it felt
right that's something that I think
about all the time something that I'll
never forget you know I thought these
charges against me were so ridiculous I
was charged with finally I was charged
with three counts of Espionage and of
course I hadn't committed Espionage uh
but I was also charged as you note with
revealing the identity of an undercover
CIA operative that identity was never
made public and at the same time that I
was being charged uh General David
Petraeus the director of the FBI was
revealing the identities of 10 CIA
covert operatives to his girlfriend and
I said to my attorneys at the time why
isn't he being charged with crime and my
attorney my lead attorney said because
he didn't blow the whistle on the cia's
torture program so in the end I actually
decided to go to trial I actually
decided that I I hadn't done anything
wrong and I said once I get in front of
a jury they'll see how ridiculous these
charges are and my lead attorney
was very angry with this decision and he
he got right in my face and he said do
you know what your problem is your
problem is you think this is about
Justice and it's not about Justice it's
about mitigating damage take the deal
and so when you spend two years right
yeah yeah you spent two years instead of
35 or 45 and
you're spending time with your kids now
exactly so ultimately was it the correct
decision
yes and it was my kids that motive
motivated me to finally take the uh the
deal because you're right it was 23
months or 45 years
what was it like in federal prison
well you know the judge recommended that
I go to a minimum security Work Camp uh
no bars on the Windows no fences no
guard towers
uh and they ignored that recommendation
and they put me in the actual prison
with child sex criminals with Mafia
Leaders with International drug kingpins
and I decided that I was trained for
this kind of thing I was going to rely
on my CIA training to keep myself safe
and at the top of the social Heap I made
strategic alliances with different gangs
or groups in prison
and I ended up getting through the 23
months incredible I think we can do
an entirely different interview just
talking about your time in prison and
maybe we'll do that someday uh which
which sounds really fascinating there's
a lot of potential there I wonder that
would be fun after after all of this
right when all is after all is said and
done you you blew the whistle you said
well they were lying about the fact that
they didn't know about waterboarding and
and some of those other
uh processes that they called enhanced
interrogation techniques
um it came out you paid a heavy price
for it when you reflect back on this
entire Journey
do you think that all of it was rotten
or was it only the fact that the CIA was
crossing the line on certain instances
so for example you were the
counter-terrorism chief in Pakistan
immediately after 9 11 a very explosive
time in the world right the United
States
um desperate for Revenge a lot of anger
among the Bush Administration and the
U.S really flexing its superpower muscle
from the stuff that you did going after
Al Qaeda going after you know suspected
terrorists was all of it wrong or was it
just the fact that you crossed the line
when it came to the the specifics of how
you try to extract information out of
detail needs
that's a great question actually
um I I do not think all of it is wrong I
believe that our immediate response
after 9 11 was a righteous War we had to
destroy Al Qaeda because it had sought
to destroy us now Iraq was wrong it was
wrong to stay in Afghanistan for for 20
years certainly uh but the the torture
issue the torture program to me was very
wrong we we like to go around the world
we Americans like go around the world
and profess to be a country that is
governed by the rule of law a country
that is a Guiding Light a Beacon of Hope
for human rights and civil rights and
civil liberties and that's just simply
not true you know on the one hand we
tell countries what they can and can't
do when it comes to civil rights and
then we run a torture program we run an
archipelago of secret prisons we kidnap
people off the streets and send them to
third countries to be tortured we're
either going to be that shining Beacon
of Hope or we're not but we can't have
it both ways um
in looking into the details of your time
in Pakistan
you were Central to the capture of Abu
zubaida and he ended up being
waterboarded 83 times and he was in all
sorts of terrible stress positions sleep
deprivation food deprivation and like
you were you were there with him at the
beginning but you weren't involved in
his torture which seems abundantly clear
however interestingly
from the testimony that came out of Abu
zubaida U.S government officials White
House officials DOD officials and the
like use this testimony to build a case
for the Iraq War making that connection
between Saddam Hussein and Al-Qaeda and
saying well we've got to go into Iraq so
when you when you think back do you do
you feel a sense of almost personal
responsibility that you nabbed this guy
and they instrumentalized him and used
him to build their case to invade Iraq
in part this is a very complicated issue
in that there were parallel sources of
intelligence uh there was the
Intelligence being the Intelligence
being provided by ahmatellabi and the
Iraqi National Congress that those of us
at the CIA knew was being fabricated but
even though it was being fabricated and
we were telling the White House that it
was false uh the office of the Vice
President Dick Cheney at the time
elected to use that phony information to
justify the Iraq War one of the ways
that Abu zabeta was very very helpful to
us well two of the ways
were that um we really didn't know
anything about Al qaeda's wiring diagram
we didn't know anything about its
structure and he's the one who told us
how the organization was structured more
importantly he told us about Khalid
Sheikh Mohammed and we we had never
heard the name Khalid Sheikh Muhammad
before we had heard the num degair
we knew that there was this very bad man
out there who meant us harm and who was
trying to come up with these different
uh plans to use planes as as weapons but
we had never heard the name Muhammad and
so it was I was a beta that allowed us
to focus our investigation now with all
of that said I'm on record as saying
that I believe abusive should be
released from Guantanamo he has been he
has been in our custody for almost 21
years now and he's never been charged
with a crime he never will be charged
with a crime because the information
used to implicate him in crimes was
gathered using torture and it's just
simply illegal so if we can't give this
man his constitutional rights uh of a
trial uh before a jury of his peers we
have to let him go
as things moved forward and the debate
kicked on in the U.S
in large part due to you and others who
were very bravely coming forward and
saying this is this is what's happening
we saw in 2015 the McCain Feinstein
resolution in the Senate
and the government taking it seriously
that torture is happening and that we
need to have new rules and we shouldn't
be doing the things that we were doing
in the immediate aftermath of the war on
terror does that mean that the CIA is no
longer torturing people
well that's what we would all like to
think and and I hope that's the case I
hope the CIA is not torturing people but
with that said you you make a very
important Point here the new rules are
that the CIA and every other national
security organization in the United
States have to abide by the rules set
forth in the Army Field Manual now the
Army Field Manual is an executive branch
document and so all that the American
government needs to do to bring back a
torture program
is with the stroke of the president's
pen change the Army Field Manual so as
things stand now we're told that there
is no torture program I would like to
believe that that's true and I would
also like to believe that that is a
permanent situation but we just don't
really know I began by asking you if
you're comfortable with the label
whistleblower
let me ask you about the other label
that did the rounds particularly
just after
the government started going after you
traitor
how did that feel
I think that the traders that we had in
government
uh were sitting in the White House
we are supposed to be as I said a nation
of laws
uh we can't just pick and choose the
laws that we want to follow and ignore
the laws that we don't want to follow if
there were any Traders uh in in
government at the time it was the
leadership at the CIA it was the
president and the vice president and the
the National Security advisor I would
put my record up against theirs any day
does it matter if the president is
left-wing or right-wing democrat or
republican whether the the house or
congress is you know one side or the
other when it comes to foreign policy
when it comes to the CIA and when it
comes to the things that the government
is willing to do or the places that
they're willing to go in order to take
care of National Security
no this is not a partisan issue at all
uh we've had democratic presidents and
Republican presidents pursuing the same
kinds of policies uh Barack Obama for
example who was supposed to have been a
left-wing president killed four times as
many people as George W bush did with
the use of drones uh so this this has
nothing to do with the domestic U.S
politics or whether somebody identifies
as a liberal or as a conservative uh
they're all in this together this is a
this is a unified unfortunately it's a
unified policy as things stand right now
with Russia's attack on Ukraine with war
raging in that particular region and
with Myriad other things going on tell
me knowing how the CIA operates what
would they be doing right now what would
their priorities be given that the
United States is not actively involved
in any specific Wars on the ground they
don't have ground troops right now tell
me what's going on in the corridors of
power in Langley
I would say two things are going on one
is training uh ukrainians in any way
possible certainly there's there's
defense department training we know that
they're being trained on high Mars and
on the use of the Abrams tank now and on
uh the Patriot missile system but at the
CIA they're doing two things they're
training uh Ukrainian Intelligence
Officers to very simply to recruit spice
to steal secrets and uh and they are
trying the best that they can to
infiltrate Russian organizations again
to steal spy to recruit spies to steal
secrets that's really what the CIA comes
down to
you
um have been on record as saying that
you recruited
I'm not sure if you said a handful of
people on nine people you can you can
verify the number now during your time
at the CIA tell me a little bit I mean
without going to jail again I don't want
to get you in trouble but tell me a
little bit about the recruitment
processes and
what those types of people would be
doing right now out there might they
might be keeping you in mind as well
because you were the guy that got them
in
yeah that's a tough one at the CIA we
have something called the uh asset
recruitment cycle it is spot
assess develop recruit uh you spot
somebody whether it's at a diplomatic
cocktail party or on the street or in a
meeting you assess their access to
information that you want you develop
them by befriending them and making sure
that you become one of their best
friends and then you formalize the
relationship by recruiting them uh you
know this is something that the cia's
been doing since 1947 and it works and
so uh so they just keep doing it it's
updated constantly because of changes in
technology of course and changes in the
cia's operating directives but uh this
is what they would be doing against the
Russians right now were you proud of
your work in general over the years oh I
was I was I was very proud of my work
you know it's funny for all the
complaints that I have about the ccia
those complaints are really about about
legality and about maintaining the rule
of law but in terms of in enjoying the
job
I enjoy every minute of it CIA sent me
to 70 countries around the world I got
to meet Kings and presidents and prime
ministers and uh it was the job of a
lifetime I just wish that uh that they
had followed the law like they were
supposed to have followed the law does
it sting that you're still
in a legal sense a convicted felon
you're free but you're a convicted felon
and of course a lot of other aspects
that come with it tangibly it affects
your life you you cannot vote and and
the like do you want to do you want to
get that monkey off your back
I do
um I I applied to have my civil rights
reinstated so I am allowed to vote now
but when I was convicted of government
confiscated my pension and as a result
if I don't get that pension back I'm
going to have to work until the day I
die I have literally nothing saved for
my retirement now
um and so you know I've got a lot of
support here in in Washington a lot of
former CIA officers 70 of them signed a
a letter to the president asking him to
Pardon Me
and so I'm going to apply for a
presidential pardon and as you correctly
say try to get this monkey off my back
do you think that Joe Biden would be
amenable to to that do you think he's if
ever there was an opportunity he'd be
the guy who might be able to do it
I think so as you might have guessed
from my name I'm a Greek American and
Joe Biden has a reputation in the Greek
American Community as being so pro-greek
American that he's called Joe
bidenopoulos and so I'm hoping that uh
you know maybe I can make a little
connection there and uh he'll take some
pity on me yeah well something very deep
into my research I was watching some of
your interviews reading a bunch of
Articles something that I just came
across in the last half hour before I
had to come in studio and talk to you
was this information that you were the
victim of uh I guess something that can
be described as a bit of a Shakedown by
some Trump officials where there was the
suggestion that Trump might pardon you
but you needed to pay some money into
installments and you paid the first
installment
but the pardon never came I mean it was
so crazy that I I thought oh my God I
want to actually delay this interview so
I can read up some more on it before I
do the interview but you know what let's
just tell us about it because it's
insane tell me more about this John
yeah this this unfortunately is how
Washington Works uh at least under the
Trump Administration pardons were
literally for sale and so I hired a
republican lobbyist uh she asked for
fifty thousand dollars up front
a fifty thousand dollars to come once I
got the pardon and she was supposed to
Lobby the president on my behalf and
eventually get me the pardon uh I never
got the pardon and toward the very end
of the Trump Administration when I
realized I wasn't going to get it I uh I
secured a meeting with Rudolph Giuliani
uh the former mayor of New York the
close friend and attorney of the
president and right to my face Giuliani
asked me for for two million dollars and
I laughed and I said I said first of all
I don't have two million dollars I'll
never have two million dollars but
secondly even if I had two million
dollars why would I spend that to
recover a seven hundred thousand dollar
pension and uh it turned out that the
FBI at the time of that meeting was
investigating Giuliani for doing exactly
this trying to sell pardon and so um I
spoke to the FBI I answered their
questions
to the best of my knowledge nothing uh
nothing has come of it or will come of
it then I never got my pardon it's
completely Bonkers it's an absolutely
ludicrous situation and it's another one
we'll have another show about that
someday um okay before we wrap up there
are a few names I'm gonna throw at you
and very briefly give me your thoughts
on them right so I'm going to start with
Edward Snowden
I think Edward Snowden is a is a bona
fide American hero without Edward
Snowden we would have no idea
that our country's intelligence agencies
were spying on us I think he did a great
national service
hmm
um Julian Assange
I am a strong supporter of Julian
Assange uh Julian Assange embarrassed
the American government but again just
like it's Snowden uh without Julian
Assange we wouldn't know about war
crimes being committed by the U.S
military and we wouldn't know about uh
the cia's capabilities in targeting
citizens
Chelsea Manning
I have a little bit of a tougher time
with Chelsea Manning why uh I know that
well
I know that for whistleblowers
motivation is irrelevant uh but Chelsea
Manning didn't provide the information
that she provided to WikiLeaks because
she intended to blow the whistle she did
it because she just didn't want to be in
the in the American Military anymore and
uh and she wanted to come home and and
this is why Chelsea Manning is not
really a participant in whistleblower
circles you know there are whistleblower
groups I I'm looking out the window of
my office right now and I can see two
different whistleblower groups across
the street and Chelsea Manning doesn't
play a role in any of those
whistleblower group she's elected to
just stay away and uh and lead her own
life very finely the thing that I said
at at the top the people who were
involved in torture didn't see any
prison time The Whistleblower you
you went to jail you lost your freedom
for for two years you you suffered in
many ways as a result of it from the
perspective of power that's deterrence
isn't it it's a lesson if anybody wants
to blow the whistle oh yes you're gonna
have to pay the price
with that in mind your message to anyone
within the CIA right now or any other
arm of government in any government not
just the United States if they want to
blow the whistle on something that is
troubling their conscience your message
to them is what
hire an attorney first
you can blow the whistle
should look whistle but have an attorney
sitting next to you when you do it
okay John kerryoku yeah I really enjoyed
this conversation I thank you very much
for joining us
today
[Music]
oh